בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is ל"ח, Lamed Chet, where
we pick up we're continuing with the discussion of מצוות התלויות בארץ
Mitzvos Hatluyos Ba'aretz and we were discussing חדש Chadash
which
we're going to continue to discuss today. I should mention that Charlie
sent out an email that first of all I was right that
the winter wheat refers to the wheat that's basically like planted in
the fall, growing over the winter, and comes and basically begins to
be harvested around the spring, and that's the... and that the עומר
Omer works for that you never have a חדש Chadash problem because
by the time it's ready to come to market the עומר Omer
is already brought and the עומר Omer is brought once it's already
taken root. It takes root over the winter. The problem is spring
wheat, because spring wheat is planted after in the spring after the
עומר Omer is brought, takes root after the עומר Omer is brought,
comes to market around ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah time, and that stuff
does not have... is you know is אסור assur until פסח, Pesach,
until the עומר Omer is brought. So anyways the email that the...
the facts that Charlie sent out, it seems that in the states
like 70 to 80 percent is winter wheat. So the argument that
רוב rov is the ישן yashan is correct, but there is differences
in terms of the gluten content and other types of things, so
sometimes you have to find out like some all-purpose flours might be
a mix, some types of wheats are specifically one type and the
other the other, like it's not just random, they actually have different
qualities, which is why by the way that pizza dough is pretty
much always ישן. yashan. That's why it's easy for these pizza places
to be, because of the sort of rising qualities, like it's chosen
to be the winter wheat.
So the winter wheat is the thing that gets you out of
the חדש Chadash problem.
Well, the winter wheat is not חדש Chadash because it's right because
it's already taken root by then, you know, and hasn't come to
market yet by the time that the עומר Omer is brought.
Now how come no one deals with... this is a major contradiction
between all these סוגיות sugyos and קהלת, Kohelet, I don't know, it
just says אין חדש. ein chadash.
Ah, there you go. Okay, very good.
Is that לכתחילה lechatchila somebody, like the...
no, no, you cannot be... I mean if they're mixing it up
then you're not being מבטל לכתחילה. mevatel lechatchila.
If you buy it and it's a mixer?
You, well, then it becomes a problem because then it would be,
question is that חדש Chadash actually, it's not only ששים, shishim, it's
a... it's
דבר שיש לו מתירים. davar sheyesh lo matirin. So תערובת ta'aroves really
wouldn't be good. You would need to argue, you know, that sort
of like a כל דפריש מרובא פריש kol deparish meruba parish type
of... it's complicated. All right, let's continue. The גמרא Gemara now picks
up where today's דף daf is ל"ח Lamed Chet but we pick
up on ל"ז עמוד ב' Lamed Zayin Amud Beis and it says
the following. We had רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael exactly around this because
by חדש Chadash it says, it says לחם וקלי וכרמל לא תאכלו
עד עצם היום הזה עד הביאכם את קרבן אלהיכם חקת עולם לדרתיכם
בכל משבתיכם. Lechem vekali vekharmel lo sokhlu ad etzem hayom hazeh ad
havi'akhem es korban elokeichem chukas olam ledoroseichem bekhol moshavoseichem.
So בכל מושבותיכם, bekhol moshavoseichem, does that mean wherever you dwell even
in חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, which is what the רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer here holds, or and that's one, or is it like the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma holds, no, it means after you've settled, and
that's the position of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael like about the נסכים,
nesachim, that מושבותיכם moshavoseichem means after you've settled into the land. So
now the גמרא Gemara is going to be bringing another opposite opinion
taught from the house of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that says the
opposite, בכל מושבותיכם bekhol moshavoseichem means wherever you dwell, not once you've
settled. So that's where we pick up. The גמרא Gemara says like
this. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, lines up with אביי Abaye about 12
lines down. אמר אביי Amar Abaye on ל"ז עמוד ב', Lamed Zayin
Amud Beis, האי תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל מפיק מהאי תנא דבי רבי
ישמעאל. hai tanna devei Rabbi Yishmael mapik mihai tanna devei Rabbi Yishmael.
The following תנא tanna from the house of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
sort of rejects the other teaching from the house of רבי ישמעאל.
Rabbi Yishmael. So there's two contradictory teachings from the house of רבי
ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. What's this
תנא? tanna? דתנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, detana devei Rabbi Yishmael, we taught
from the house of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, הואיל ונאמרו ביאות בתורה
סתם, ho'il vene'emru biyos batorah stam, since the תורה Torah often speaks
about כי תבוא אל הארץ ki savo el ha'aretz without clarifying, ופרט
לך הכתוב באחת מהן לאחר ירושה וישיבה, uferat lekha haksav be'achas mehen
le'achar yerushe viyeshiva, and in one place it speaks about after you've
settled, okay, which is what? Which is, which is, we'll take a
look,
I'm sorry, by the king it says כי תבא אל הארץ וירשתה
וישבת בה. ki savo el ha'aretz veyirashto veyashavta bah. So that's not
just the word בכל מושבותיכם bekhol moshavoseichem that's explicitly right taking possession
of it and settling into it, which is the concept that we're
going to... we linked to בכל מושבותיכם. bekhol moshavoseichem. So he says
in one place it explicitly says that, אף כל לאחר ירושה וישיבה.
af kol le'achar yerushe viyeshiva. Whenever it says כי תבוא, ki savo,
even without the בכל מושבותיכם, bekhol moshavoseichem, any כי תבוא ki savo
means after you've settled in it
and you know after you've settled and possessed
it after the 14 years.
Is it כלל ופרט? klal u'prat? In other words if סתם stam
and then ופרש. u'pareish. No. Is that a similar logic?
Yeah, that's interesting but it's... the hermeneutic here is... But, but the
hermeneutic here is בנין אב. Binyan Av. That we have one example
in the תורה. Torah. So you're right, in a way, in this
case, it clarifies, it's true, it clarifies that entry does not mean
entry immediately. It's the specific circumstances of settling, but then it serves
as a בנין אב Binyan Av for elsewhere. Okay. So, anyway, so
this is the issue. Not what בכל מושבותיכם B’chol Moshvoteichem means, but
whether we normally assume when it speaks about something applies when you
enter the land, do we automatically assume it means after you've settled
the land? Or does it mean as soon as you cross into
the land? Okay. ואידך, V’idach, the other תנא דבי ר' ישמעאל, Tanna
de-bei Rabbi Ishmael, was that says that it has to say מושבותיכם
moshvoteichem to mean after you've settled, משום דבי מלך וביכורים שני כתובים
הבאים כאחד. mishum d’bei Melech u-Bikkurim sheni ketuvim ha-ba’im k’echad. No, you
cannot use this as a בנין אב, Binyan Av, as a paradigm,
because there's another פסוק pasuk where it also spells it out. And
again, as we've learned, when it makes two things explicit, they're to
be understood as exceptions. וכל שני כתובים הבאים כאחד אין מלמדין. V’chol
sheni ketuvim ha-ba’im k’echad ein melamdin. Okay, so by the ביכורים, Bikkurim,
what does it say by the ביכורים? Bikkurim? It says והיה כי
תבוא אל הארץ. V’hayah ki tavo el ha-aretz. And it says, you
know, וירשתה וישבת בה. v’yarashta v’yashavta bah. What? ולקחת מראשית כל פרי
האדמה.
v’lakachta m’reishit
kol pri ha-adamah.
Exactly. So since in two places it clarifies that entry after you've
settled, it means when it normally talks about entry without clarifying, it
means only entry. ואידך, V’idach, and the other would say צריכי. tzrichi.
No, it has to tell me both places that it means to
be settled, but they're not to be read as exceptions.
דאי כתב רחמנא מלך ולא כתב ביכורים הוה אמינא, D’ei katav rachmana
Melech v’lo katav Bikkurim hava amina, I would assume ביכורים דקא מיתהני
לאלתר. Bikkurim d’ka mit’hani l’altar. I would have said, okay, the general
rule is anytime it says entry, it means after you've settled. But
by ביכורים Bikkurim I would have said there it means literally as
soon as you walk in, because you immediately get the benefit of
the fruit. So therefore it had to clarify, no, no, this fits
the rule, this also's only after you've settled. But the clarification is
not to tell you it's an exception, to tell you no, no,
this is also part of the rule.
ואי כתב ביכורים, V’ei katav Bikkurim, had it said by ביכורים Bikkurim
it means after you've settled, ולא כתב מלך, v’lo katav Melech, and
not a king, הוה אמינא, hava amina, מלך דדרכו לכבוש לאלתר. Melech
d’darko lichbosh l’altar. I would have said, of course, the whole first
14 years are conquering and settling the land. So of course you
need a king at the beginning, not after. Oh, first settle the
land, then make yourself a king. You need a king to wage
the wars. Okay? So therefore it had to spell out that no,
even the king, that's only after you've settled the land. But both,
the reason it spells it out is to clarify, but it's not
to say they're exceptions, they're still part of the rule. ואידך, V’idach,
and the one that says no, that they are that it says
it twice makes them exceptions. The rule is כי תבוא ki tavo
is that normally it means immediately. He would say back, ליכתב רחמנא
מלך ולא בעי ביכורים. Lichtav rachmana Melech v’lo ba’ei Bikkurim. Look, it
could have just written King, and then I could have inferred
ביכורים. Bikkurim. ואנא אמינא ומה מלך דלכבוש אחרי ירושה וישיבה. V’ana amina
umah Melech d’lichbosh acharei yerushah v’yeshivah. If the king, that you normally
need a king to conquer the land, and even that is only
after you've settled, ביכורים לא כל שכן, Bikkurim lo kol shekein, how
much more so ביכורים Bikkurim should only be after you settle. And
since it spells out ביכורים, Bikkurim, that's to teach me that those
are the exceptions, but the general rule is as soon as you
enter the land. ואידך, V’idach, the other would say back, אי כתב
הכי הוה אמינא, Ei katav hachi hava amina,
it would be like חלה Challah because by חלה Challah we know
that חלה Challah actually applies immediately. Because by חלה Challah it doesn't
say כי תבוא, ki tavo, it says בבואכם. b’vo’achem. And the גמרא
Gemara learns out elsewhere that the בבואכם b’vo’achem by חלה, Challah, חלה
Challah does apply immediately when you enter the land. So I would
have said ביכורים Bikkurim would be like חלה. Challah. They're called the
same type of a thing, you know, they're both the first gift
to the כהן Kohen and so on. So therefore that's why I
would have said that even though the rule is after you've settled,
I would have said ביכורים Bikkurim would have followed חלה. Challah. קמשמע
לן Kamashma lan that it's not that way. Okay. So that was
again a little bit of a little bit off of our immediate
topic, but just to sort of clarify. What we have is the
following. We have right, we have the we have the, you know,
we have the כי תבואו ki tavo’u plus
ארץ מושבותיכם, eretz moshvoteichem, מושבותיכם moshvoteichem or בכל מושבותיכם, b’chol moshvoteichem, בכל
מושבותיכם. b’chol moshvoteichem. Right, so that ר' ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael says that
that means, well, both he says, because this is חדש, chadash, okay,
and this is נסכים, nesachim, okay, and that ר' ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael
says after the first 14 years. Okay. And that's what that's that
תנא דבי ר' ישמעאל, Tanna de-bei Rabbi Ishmael, but you need both.
You need the כי תבואו ki tavo’u and the מושבותיכם. moshvoteichem. And
only that means after the first 14 years after ירושה וישיבה. yerushah
v’yeshivah. As opposed to this ר' ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael which says any
כי תבוא ki tavo automatically means all כי תבוא ki tavo just
by itself means after 14 after the first 14 years, after ירושה
וישיבה. yerushah v’yeshivah.
Okay. So that's what the debate is. And where does it say
כי תבוא ki tavo by itself? Okay, so that's so that's the
general debate. Is it כי תבוא ki tavo plus מושבותיכם moshvoteichem or
just כי תבוא? ki tavo? And the question is whether you learn
it out from the paradigm of
of ביכורים, Bikkurim, what do you call it? Of ביכורים Bikkurim and
מלך. Melech. By מלך Melech it says, what does it say by
מלך? Melech? Now I forgot. What does the פסוק pasuk say by
מלך? Melech? כי תבוא
אל הארץ וירשתה, Ki tavo el ha-aretz v’yarashta, right, כי
תבוא אל הארץ. Ki tavo el ha-aretz. וירשתה, Viyarashta,
that's מלך, Melech, and what does it say by
ביכורים?
Bikkurim? וירשתה וישבת. Viyarashta Veyashavta.
כי תבוא אל הארץ וירשתה
וישבת.
Ki Tavo El Haaretz
Viyarashta Veyashavta.
See, same thing:
כי תבוא אל הארץ וירשתה וישבת. Ki Tavo El Haaretz Viyarashta Veyashavta.
Okay, same thing. Okay, so those are the two places where it
says כי תבוא Ki Tavo and וירשתה. Viyarashta. So anyway, the question
is, is כי תבוא Ki Tavo enough to tell you ירושה וישיבה?
Yerusha Viyeshiva? So one says it is. Okay, that's not שני כתובים
הבאים כאחד, Shnei Ketuvim Haba'im Ke'echad, each one was necessary. And the
other says no, those are exceptions and כי תבוא Ki Tavo is
not enough, you need it to explicitly say וירשתה Viyarashta or מושבותיכם
Moshvoteichem etc. Okay, so that's the general question whether these things apply
right away or whether they apply after fourteen years. But for us,
what is relevant in terms of the חדש Chodesh issue is in
this, that according still within this, regardless of which approach you take,
מושבותיכם Moshvoteichem means after you've settled. As opposed to a very different
read, which is that מושבותיכם Moshvoteichem means wherever you dwell, which would
mean that חדש Chodesh applies immediately in חוצה לארץ. Chutz La'aretz.
What was the last point about the חלה? Challah?
Yeah, that חלה Challah specifically does take place immediately. Because of the
פסוק pasuk by חלה Challah it says בבואכם, Bivo'achem,
which is meant to mean immediately. So I would have thought that
since חלה Challah takes place immediately, ביכורים Bikkurim takes place immediately, and
therefore and therefore I would have therefore the fact that it says
it a second time by ביכורים, Bikkurim, וירשתה, Viyarashta, does not signal
that it's an exception, it is the rule, it's just telling me
don't put ביכורים Bikkurim with חלה.
Challah. Why wouldn't I say the same thing about מלך? Melech?
No, because ביכורים Bikkurim and חלה Challah are essentially the same thing.
They're both the same types of yeah, and they're both they're both
מתנות, matanot, they're both called תרומה, terumah, they both go to the
כהן, Kohen, they both have the same status. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
השתא Hashta says the גמרא, Gemara, where were we? Okay, השתא דאמרת
חובת הגוף נוהגת בין בארץ בין בחוצה לארץ, Hashta De'amart Chovat Haguf
Noheget Bein Ba'aretz Bein Bechutz La'aretz, מושבותיכם דכתב רחמנא גבי שבת למה
לי? Moshvoteichem Dechtav Rachmana Gabei Shabbat Lama Li? Fine.
Now we've got the idea that personal obligations apply in חוצה לארץ.
Chutz La'aretz. Now we've got to get back to this question that
we raised, which is מושבותיכם, Moshvoteichem, why does it say it by
שבת? Shabbat? First of all, it can't mean after you've settled the
land, שבת Shabbat applied right away. Anyway it also says, you know,
so why does it say מושבותיכם? Moshvoteichem? What's the relevance of that?
If מושב moshav normally, I mean if מושב moshav meant anywhere you
dwell we understand it, but if מושב moshav normally means after you've
settled the land, what is the point of saying the word מושב
moshav by שבת? Shabbat? It's completely inappropriate. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says מושבותיכם דכתב רחמנא בשבת למה לי? Moshvoteichem Dechtav Rachmana BeShabbat Lama
Li? Right? שבת היא לה' בכל מושבותיכם Shabbat Hi Lashem Bechol Moshvoteichem
is the פסוק pasuk by שבת. Shabbat. So למה לי? lama li?
איצטריך, Itzterich, I need it. סלקא
דעתך אמינא, Salka Da'atach Amina,
since it's written in the same פרשה parsha there in אמור Emor
with the other מועדים, mo'adim, תיבעי קידוש כמיעודים, Tibay Kiddush KeMo'adim,
maybe it would need קידוש החודש Kiddush HaChodesh like the like you
know like all the other מועדות mo'adot because they're they depend on
when ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh is established. So maybe you would have
to even though שבת Shabbat occurs every the same day every week,
maybe you'd have to say like מקודש מקודש Mekudash Mekudash to make
it into שבת. Shabbat. קא משמע לן,
Ka
Mashma
Lan, קא משמע לן Ka Mashma Lan that there since it says
בכל מושבותיכם bechol moshvoteichem it means outside of Israel, you know, where
it's not, you know, קידוש החודש Kiddush HaChodesh happens in Israel, so
בכל מושבותיכם bechol moshvoteichem is emphasizing that this has no dependence on
what goes on in the land of Israel and it applies automatically
without any aspect of sanctifying it. That's why it's emphasizing it, because
obviously I know it's בכל מושבותיכם. bechol moshvoteichem. We do make קידוש?
Kiddush? What? We make קידוש Kiddush and there's a basic whole idea
about how the קידוש Kiddush we make does like add some human
level of קדושה, kedusha, but nevertheless in principle you don't need it.
So that's why even though yes it is obvious it applies everywhere,
the תורה Torah still had to say בכל מושבותיכם. bechol moshvoteichem. Okay,
now we're going to go through other places the תורה Torah talks
about מושבותיכם moshvoteichem to understand why it's said if we would have
anyway known that it applies everywhere. So the גמרא Gemara says by
חלב ודם chelev vedam it says בכל מושבותיכם. bechol moshvoteichem.
So the גמרא Gemara says where were we?
מושב דכתב רחמנא גבי חלב ודם, Moshav Dechtav Rachmana Gabei Chelev Vedam,
it says don't eat חלב ודם, chelev vedam, you know, fat and
the blood בכל מושבותיכם. bechol moshvoteichem. So why did it have to
say that? למה לי? Lama li? Of course it's true, it's not
land-based. So of course it applies everywhere. So the גמרא Gemara says
איצטריך, itsterich, right? סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka Da'atach Amina, since it's in
the context of קרבנות, korbanot, בזמן
דאיכא קרבן ניתסר חלב ודם,
Bezman De'ika Korban
Nitesar Chelev Vedam, when there's קרבנות korbanot then it's forbidden because then
it belongs on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. בזמן דליכא קרבן לא, Bezman Delika
Korban Lo, and when there's no קרבן korban no, and maybe at
least by the חלב chelev you see that the חלב chelev of
a חיה chaya doesn't isn't אסור assur because that doesn't go on
the מזבח. mizbe'ach. קא משמע לן Ka Mashma Lan that it applies
like at all places, but also meaning in all times, not in
the context of the מקדש. Mikdash. מושב דכתב רחמנא גבי מצה ומרור
Moshav Dechtav Rachmana Gabei Matzah UMaror למה לי? lama li? There you
go. See, now it's a little עניינא דיומא. inyana deyoma. בכל מושבותיכם
תאכלו מצות. Bechol moshvoteichem tochelu matzot. So why you need it? איצטריך,
Itsterich, you need it. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka Da'atach Amina, על מצות
ומרורים יאכלוהו, Al matzot umerorim yochelohu, that fundamentally מצה matzah and מרור
maror is part of the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So therefore בזמן
דאיכא פסח אין, Bezman de'ika Pesach in, only when there's a פסח.
Pesach. בזמן דליכא פסח לא, Bezman delika Pesach lo, not. קא משמע
לן, Ka Mashma Lan, which is relevant to now. Actually is a
very reasonable read of the פסוקים. pesukim. It's a very big question
how we know מצה matzo applies nowadays without the קרבן פסח. Korban
Pesach. So here we're saying בכל מושבתיכם bechol moshvoteichem again, the combination
of everywhere and every time, everywhere means outside of the context or
of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it means even if you're in
exile, after the חורבן בית המקדש, churban Beis HaMikdash, when you're not
in the land of Israel, even then מצה matzo applies. Of course
the irony is of course מרור maror doesn't apply and it really
is dependent on the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, and מצה matzo the
גמרא Gemara learns that from another פסוק, pasuk, but okay, exactly. Okay,
now דכתיב רחמנא גבי תפילין ופטר חמור למה לי. de-chtiv Rachmana gabei
tefillin u-peter chamor lama li. Remember we mentioned that the other day
when it says
by תפילין tefillin and פטר חמור peter chamor it says כי תבוא
אל הארץ ki tavo el ha-aretz when you come to the land
and your child will say,
what is this מצוה, mitzvah, and והעברת כל פטר רחם להשם ve-ha'avarta
kol peter rechem l-Hashem etc. Anyway, but פטר חמור peter chamor and
תפילין tefillin are not limited to coming into the land. So why
does it say when you enter the land? So הוא מיבעי ליה
לכדתניא hu mibai lei le-che-de-tanya like we learned דבי רבי ישמעאל, de-bei
Rabi Yishmael, again רבי ישמעאל Rabi Yishmael teaches,
עשה מצוה זו asei mitzvah zo do this מצוה mitzvah or these
מצוות mitzvos I guess, שבשבילה תכנס לארץ she-bi-shvilah tikanes la-aretz that on
its merit you will enter into the land. So the idea of
mentioning ביכורים bikurim and תפילין tefillin is that not that that's only
applies when you enter the land, but that פטר חמור—excuse peter chamor
me, what'd I say? ביכורים? bikurim? I'm sorry. פטר חמור peter chamor
and תפילין, tefillin, I meant to say בכור. bechor. Anyway, פטר חמור
peter chamor and תפילין tefillin is not that you only do it
when you enter the land, but it merits your entering the land.
Why? I don't know what's special about those two. Okay, but it's
a way of dealing with the dependency of the פסוק pasuk by
reversing the dependency. בשלמא למאן דאמר מושב כל מקום שאתם יושבים משמע.
bishlama le-man de-amar moshav kol makom she-atem yoshvim mashma. Okay, now we
switch back to חדש chadash which is our primary focus, also very
relevant as we've been saying. Now, בשלמא למאן דאמר מושב כל מקום
שאתם יושבים משמע, bishlama le-man de-amar moshav kol makom she-atem yoshvim mashma,
if מושב moshav means wherever you dwell and חדש chadash applies in
חוץ לארץ, chutz la-aretz, that's really the point. If חדש chadash applies
in חוץ לארץ chutz la-aretz like רבי אליעזר Rabi Eliezer says, היינו
דכתיב ויאכלו מעבור הארץ ממחרת הפסח. hainu de-chtiv va-yochlu me-avur ha-aretz mi-mochoras
ha-Pesach. So now we're talking יהושע, Yehoshua, it says they ate from
the produce of the land from the day following פסח. Pesach. So
that sounds like they were only allowed to eat the day after
פסח. Pesach. ממחרת הפסח אכול, mi-mochoras ha-Pesach achol,
they only ate the day after פסח Pesach on the sixteenth of
ניסן Nissan when there was the עומר. Omer. Okay, I don't know
if they were bringing the עומר Omer then, they didn't have
a central מקדש Mikdash at that stage, but whatever, anyway, according to
חז"ל, Chazal, the עומר, Omer, the sixteenth itself is מתיר matir the
eating of חדש. chadash. So on the day after פסח Pesach on
the sixteenth they ate from the new grain of the land. מעיקרא
לא אכול, mei-ikara lo achol, but they couldn't eat beforehand because it
was still חדש. chadash.
אלמא אקריבו עומר, alma akrivu Omer, you see the עומר Omer was
brought. So the גמרא Gemara here actually says that it sounds like
they did actually bring the עומר. Omer. Okay, anyway, so but something
happened on the sixteenth, they brought the עומר Omer in the I
guess the traveling משכן Mishkan and that allowed them to eat from
the grain of the land the day after פסח. Pesach. אלמא אקריבו
עומר והדר אכול alma akrivu Omer ve-hadar achol and then they ate.
אלא למאן דאמר לאחר ירושה וישיבה, ela le-man de-amar le-achar yerusha ve-yeshiva,
so now it's not the question of everywhere versus only in ארץ
ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, it's the linked part. Remember, בכל מושבתיכם bechol moshvoteichem
by חדש chadash has two possible meanings. One is everywhere, and the
other is after you've settled the land. So if it means everywhere
and now they're in Israel, they're eating from עבור הארץ, avur ha-aretz,
from the grain of the land, but you understand why it was
forbidden because basically חדש chadash applies in all places and it applies
in Israel as soon as you enter the land and it applies
in all grain everywhere. So therefore they couldn't eat the grain until
they brought the עומר. Omer.
But if ארץ מושב, Eretz Moshav, but if בכל מושבתיכם bechol moshvoteichem
by חדש chadash means after you've settled the land, so that's only
after the first fourteen years. So here they had just entered the
land in the time of יהושע, Yehoshua, why couldn't they eat the
grain immediately? Why did they have to wait till the sixteenth of
ניסן? Nissan? One minute. אלא למאן דאמר לאחר ירושה וישיבה, ela le-man
de-amar le-achar yerusha ve-yeshiva,
but if the obligation is only in the land of Israel and
only after it's been settled and conquered, conquered and settled, so ניכלו
לאלתר, neichlu le-altar, why not eat immediately? The גמרא Gemara says, you
know what, they could have, but לאו מיצטריכי, lav mitzterichi, they just
didn't need to. It was just by chance that they waited till
the sixteenth of ניסן Nissan and nothing to do with the עומר.
Omer. So why did they not need it until then? דכתיב ובני
ישראל אכלו את המן ארבעים שנה עד בואם אל ארץ נושבת. de-chtiv
u-venei Yisrael achlu es ha-man arbaim shana ad bo'am el eretz nosheves.
They ate the מן man for forty years until they came to
the settled land. את המן אכלו עד בואם אל קצה ארץ כנען.
es ha-man achlu ad bo'am el ketzei eretz Canaan. They ate it
until they came to the edge of the land of כנען. Canaan.
אי אפשר לומר עד בואם אל ארץ נושבת, ee efshar lomar ad
bo'am el eretz nosheves, you can't say they actually entered into the
land, שכבר
נאמר אל קצה ארץ כנען. she-kevar ne'emar el ketzei eretz Canaan. They
ate it until before they entered the land. ואי אפשר לומר אל
קצה ארץ כנען, ve-ee efshar lomar el ketzei eretz Canaan, you can't
say they only ate it until before they entered the land, שכבר
נאמר עד בואם אל ארץ נושבת, she-kevar ne'emar ad bo'am el eretz
nosheves, until it speaks about them having entered the land. So when
did they stop eating the מן? man? Before they entered the land
or after they entered the land, right? ארץ נושבת eretz nosheves sounds
once they actually entered into the land and קצה ketzei means they
stopped eating it when they were at the cusp of entering it.
So which one is it? הא כיצד, ha keitzad, how do you
explain it?
בשבעה באדר מת משה. be-shiva be-Adar meis Moshe. משה Moshe died
on the
seventh of אדר, Adar, which will clarify... like a month and a
week later is when they actually entered the land and that's the
verse that says they ate from the grain of the land, so
the מן man that was left in their vessels, one day's worth
of מן man satisfied them, you know, for the next 30, 37
days. Okay, and so, now the גמרא Gemara asks, wait. Well,
yes, but that's where we're going to get the number in a
minute, but hold on. But anyway, okay, so therefore, so because we
have a פסוק pasuk that says they stopped eating the מן man
before they entered, and a פסוק pasuk that says they stopped eating
the מן man when they entered, we say the מן man fell,
stopped falling right when משה Moshe died, when they were at the
cusp of entering, but they continued eating from that last falling of
the מן man until they actually entered the land. Why that is
relevant, well I guess that was one place where there was not
a leftover problem. Well, the problem is that you're not supposed to
leave leftovers, but that was one place apparently where that stopped to
apply. So anyway, the relevance for us is is that we say
that they were eating the מן man after they entered the land.
So therefore, now there's nowhere it tells you how, maybe
they entered the land before the sixteenth. We're going to see they
basically entered the land on the tenth. Okay, but nevertheless, because we're
saying they continued eating the מן man when they entered the land,
it allows us to say that they kept on eating it until
the sixteenth, and when they ate from the grain, it had nothing
to do with the איסור חדש, issur chadash, it had to just
do with the fact they didn't need the new grain until then.
So again, if חדש chadash applies בכל מושבותיכם bechol moshvoteichem everywhere and
therefore also in the land of Israel immediately, then you have to
explain well why didn't they eat from it immediately? Well, because they
had מן. man. But if you say מושבותיכם moshvoteichem means only in
the land of Israel and, wait, did I just say that wrong?
You said the opposite. If it applies immediately, that's why they had
to bring the עומר.
omer. I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I said it wrong. If, right, because,
I'm sorry, I said it wrong. If בכל מושבותיכם bechol moshvoteichem means
everywhere, including the land of Israel and including immediately, that the איסור
חדש issur chadash applied, that's why they needed to bring the עומר
omer and that's why they only ate from the מן man on
the sixteenth after they after they brought the עומר. omer. But if
מושבותיכם moshvoteichem means only in the land of Israel and only after
they settled the land, then they really were allowed to eat the
grain immediately because the עומר omer did not yet apply, the חדש
chadash did not yet apply, but they just didn't because they didn't
need it. Now I want to just say one other interesting thing
about תוספות Tosafot here raises a really good question. תוספות Tosafot in
מסכת פסחים, Masechet Pesachim, if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, it's one
of the few תוספות, Tosafots, if not the only one, that quotes
the אבן עזרא. Ibn Ezra. Take a look here on לז עמוד
ב, lamed zayin amud bet, famous תוספות Tosafot he says, הזכיר רב
אברהם אבן עזרא. Hizkir Rav Avraham Ibn Ezra. So the אבן עזרא
Ibn Ezra asks, היכי אמרינן ממחרת הפסח דהכא הוי ששה עשר בניסן?
Heichi amrinan mimochorat hapesach dechacha havah shishah asar beNisan? It's a very
nice read to say the day after פסח, Pesach, on the sixteenth
of ניסן, Nisan, they ate the new grain because they brought the
חדש chadash like ממחרת השבת, mimochorat haShabbat, which we say which we
say means, you know, the day after the first day of פסח.
Pesach. But he says there's a problem: שמא נקרא פסח דילמא ממחרת
שחיטת הפסח קאמר דהיינו טו בניסן. Shema nikra pesach dilma mimochorat shechitat
hapesach ka'amar dehaynu tet vav beNisan.
The word פסח Pesach in the תורה Torah means the offering of
the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, which was on the fourteenth, and ממחרת
הפסח mimochorat hapesach in the תורה Torah means on the fifteenth, ועדיין
לא נקרב העומר. ve'adayin lo nikrav ha'omer. So ממחרת הפסח mimochorat hapesach
would mean the fifteenth and the עומר omer hadn't been brought. והכי
נמי אשכחן בפרשת מסעי דכתיב ממחרת הפסח יצאו
בני ישראל מארץ מצרים—they Ve'hachi nami askinan beparshat masei dechtiv mimochorat hapesach
yatztu benei Yisrael me'eretz Mitzrayim left the land of Egypt the day
after פסח Pesach means the day after the bringing of the פסח,
Pesach, on the fifteenth, ואין יצאו בטו. ve'ein yatztu be'tet vav. Okay?
So that's a really good question. All right. So he says like
this: So רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam has one answer, but we're going
to skip to the nicer the better answer is three lines from
the bottom he says like this, okay: ורי מפרש ניהי דבעלמא ממחרת
הפסח הוי טו. V're'i mefaresh nihayei d'be'alma mimochorat hapesach havah tet vav.
Normally ממחרת הפסח mimochorat hapesach means after the שחיטת הפסח shechitat hapesach
and means the fifteenth, and that's clearly what it means in the
תורה. Torah. פסח Pesach is the bringing of the פסח, Pesach, and
ממחרת mimochorat is the fifteenth, is the first day of יום טוב.
Yom Tov. הכא רצה לומר טז. Hacha ratza lomar tet zayin.
Here it means the after on the sixteenth, and פסח Pesach is
going to see we'll see in just a minute it means the
eating of the פסח, Pesach, not the bringing. So the bringing was
the fourteenth, but the eating was the fifteenth. We eat it at
night, well at night is halachically the fifteenth, until
חצות, chatzot, right?
Doesn't matter, it's halachically the fifteenth, so the day after the eating
of the פסח Pesach is the sixteenth. ולשון תורה לחוד ולשון נביאים
לחוד. V'lashon Torah l'chud v'lashon nevi'im l'chud.
There's the way the תורה Torah talks and the way the נביאים
nevi'im talk, because this is a פסוק pasuk in יהושע. Yehoshua. ולשון
חכמים לחוד. V'lashon chachamim l'chud. And and normally we say לשון תורה
לחוד לשון חכמים לחוד, lashon Torah l'chud, lashon chachamim l'chud, he's inserting
לשון נביאים לחוד. lashon nevi'im l'chud. ועל כרחך צריך לומר כן דאם
לא כן אמאי איצטריך למימר מקלה לא אכל היינו לחלק v'al korchach
tzarich lomar ken d'im lo ken amai itztarich lemeimar mikla lo achal
haynu lechaleik et cetera, דעדיין לא איקרב d'adyei lo ikrav et cetera,
אלא פשיטא ela peshita last line דרצה לומר טז דהיינו ממחרת אכילת
הפסח והא דפרשת מסעי רצה
ממחרת שחיטת הפסח. d'ratza lomar tet zayin dehaynu mimochorat achilat hapesach v'had
d'parshat masei ratza mimochorat shechitat hapesach. So תוספות Tosafot says, and here's
an important point as we're coming into פסח, Pesach, פסח Pesach does
not mean the יום טוב Yom Tov of חג המצות. Chag HaMatzot.
So ממחרת... mimochorat... פסח *Pesach* does not mean the day after the
first day of of חג המצות *Chag HaMatzos*. פסח *Pesach* only means
one thing, it means the קרבן פסח *Korban Pesach*. So ממחרת הפסח
*Mimacharas HaPesach*, therefore, would normally mean the 15th. So how can you
connect the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* about eating the חדש Chadash, *Chadash* on
the day on the 15th, you know with the עומר Omer *Omer*,
eating the grain with the עומר Omer *Omer*? The עומר *Omer* is
on the 16th. So תוספות׳s *Tosafos's* answer is is that we have
to say that here it means the day after the eating of
the פסח *Pesach*, not the day after the שחיטה *shechting* of the
פסח *Pesach*, even though in the תורה Torah *Torah* it's the emphasis
is the שחיטה *shechting* of the פסח *Pesach*, here it means after
the eating. But the interesting thing about this as well is that
this
פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is quoted in part of the whole polemics with
the Samaritans and later with the Karaites about whether what ממחרת השבת
*Mimacharas HaShabbos* means by the bringing of the עומר *Omer*. Does it
mean after שבת *Shabbos*? חזל *Chazal* say it means after יום טוב
*Yom Tov*, after the first day of יום טוב *Yom Tov*. To
say look, see, it means after the first day of יום טוב
*Yom Tov*, because the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* in יהושע *Yehoshua* that speaks
about them eating the new grain, speaks about it being ממחרת הפסח
*Mimacharas HaPesach*. So you see that שבת *Shabbos* here means פסח *Pesach*.
The only problem is is that as תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* points out,
the פשט p'shat *pshat* of that פסוקים psukim, *psukim* is that there
פסח *Pesach* means the day after the 14th, not the day after
the 15th. So it doesn't exactly, you know, the פשט *pshat* of,
if you want to bring a proof from פשט *pshat* of the
פסוקים *psukim*, the פשט *pshat* of the פסוקים *psukim* don't line up
with חזל *Chazal* either. Okay. So anyway, yeah, so was your other
question Michael?
Yeah, so just to make sure, the עומר
*Omer*
which is a barley, we said applies equally to wheat and the
barley, and then the שתי הלחם *Shtei HaLechem* which is מתיר *matir*
new flour for קרבנות *korbanos*, right? That was the point in that?
Yep. All right. Okay? Everybody got it? So we have a פסוק
*pasuk* that sounds like that the פשט *pshat* of, at least the
way we're reading the פסוק *pasuk*, it sounds like חדש Chadash, *Chadash*
applied immediately in ישראל *Israel*, the land of ישראל *Israel*, which would
indicate that מושבותיכם *Moshavoseichem* means everywhere you are, it doesn't mean after
it's settled. Okay, but then the, and so how do you deal
with it? So one says oh, it wasn't about the עומר *Omer*,
that was just about the מן *man* ran out, that was the
time the מן *man* ran out. But if you read it about
the עומר *Omer* you have these other problems which on the one
hand you can say lines up with the idea of ממחרת השבת
*Mimacharas HaShabbos* meaning the day after יום טוב *Yom Tov*, but then
you've got the problem תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* raised that פסח *Pesach* does
not mean, the פשט *pshat* of the word פסח *Pesach* does not
mean the first day of יום טוב *Yom Tov*, the 15th of
ניסן Nisan *Nissan*, the פשט *pshat* of the word פסח *Pesach* means
the day the פסח *Pesach* is brought, which is the 14th of
ניסן *Nissan*.
And also what's interesting here is since מן *man* and grain are
all around... Well, right. We're talking about the food. Right. Because I
know there's a לחם מן השמים *Lechem Min HaShamayim* as well.
Totally. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara *Gemara* continues. תניא Tanya, אידך
*Tanya ida*, we taught in another ברייתא braita. *braisa*. ובני ישראל אכלו
את המן ארבעים שנה *Ubnei Yisrael achlu es haman arbaim shana*. They
ate it for 40 years. וכי ארבעים שנה אכלו *Vechi arbaim shana
achlu*? Did they really eat it for 40 years? ולא ארבעים שנה
חסר שלשים יום אכלו *Velo arbaim shana chaser shloshim yom achlu*. It
was 40 years minus 30 days because it only fell as רש״י
Rashi *Rashi* quotes the פסוקים *psukim*, but it didn't start falling the
day they left מצרים *Mitzrayim*, it fell a month later. Okay. What?
עמוד *Amud*... Oh come on. So anyway, that wouldn't be any fun.
אלא לומר לך עוגה שהוציאו ממצרים טעמו בהם טעם מן *Ela lomar
lacha ugah shehotziu miMitzrayim ta'amu bahem ta'am man*. So it was like
they ate it for 40 years because the first month before they
had מן *man* and they were still eating the cakes they brought
out of מצרים *Mitzrayim*, okay, interesting, they didn't make חמץ *chametz* because
they were too busy baking מצה *matzah*, so they were still, well
maybe you're right, maybe it means עוגות מצות *ugot matzos*. Anyway, I
don't know if those cakes were חמץ׳דיק *chametz-dik* or מצה׳דיק *matzah-dik*, but
anyway it tasted like the מן *man*. So it was like they
ate it for 40 years because the first month it was already
like a foretaste of the מן *man*. All right, so now the
גמרא gemara *Gemara* says like this. פארשפייז *Forshpeis*, exactly. תניא אידך *Tanya
ida*, we've done another ברייתא *braisa*. בשבעה באדר מת משה בשבעה באדר
נולד *Beshiva b'Adar meis Moshe, beshiva b'Adar nolad*. He was died on
the 7th of אדר *Adar* and he was born on the 7th
of אדר *Adar*. מנין שבשבעה באדר מת משה *Minayin shebeshiva b'Adar meis
Moshe*? How do you know he died on the 7th of אדר
*Adar*? שנאמר וימת שם משה עבד ה׳ *Shene'emar Vayamos sham Moshe eved
Hashem*. משה *Moshe* died there in ערבות מואב *Arvos Moav*, וכתיב ויבכו
בני ישראל את משה בערבות מואב שלשים יום *uksiv Vayivku bnei Yisrael
es Moshe b'Arvos Moav shloshim yom*. He was mourned, he was cried
over for 30 days. וכתיב ויהי אחרי מות משה עבד ה׳ *Uksiv
Vayehi acharei mos Moshe eved Hashem*. And it was after משה *Moshe*
died the beginning of ספר יהושע *Sefer Yehoshua*. וכתיב משה עבדי מת
ועתה קום עבור *Uksiv Moshe avdi meis ve'ata kum avor*. משה *Moshe*
has now died, go and cross over. So apparently it's 30 days
after משה׳s *Moshe's* death. Okay. וכתיב
*Uksiv*, and it says עברו בקרב המחנה וצוו את העם לאמר הכינו
לכם צידה *Ivru bekerev hamachane vetzivu es ha'am lemor hachinu lachem tzeidah*.
Prepare yourselves provisions. כי בעוד שלשת ימים אתם עוברים את הירדן *Ki
be'od shlosha yamim ta'avru es haYardein*. In three days אתם עוברים את
הירדן *Atem ovrim es haYardein*, you'll cross over the Jordan River. וכתיב
והעם עלו מן הירדן בעשור לחדש הראשון *Uksiv Vaha'am alu min haYardein
be'asor lachodesh harishon*. So they came up on the 10th. So basically
there was a month of mourning, three days of preparation, and then
they crossed the Jordan on the 10th of ניסן *Nissan*. So you
subtract from the 10th of ניסן *Nissan* one month and three days
and you get to the 7th of אדר *Adar*. Okay, that was
not such a hard computation. Okay. צא מהן שלשים ושלשה ימים למפרע
*Tzei mehein shloshim ushlosha
yamim l'mafrea*. 33 days, 30 for the mourning and three for the
preparation.
הא למדת שבשבעה
באדר מת משה *Ha lamedata shebeshiva b'Adar meis Moshe*. He died on
the 7th of אדר *Adar*. ומנין שבשבעה באדר נולד משה *Uminayin shebeshiva
b'Adar nolad Moshe*? How do you know he was born on the
7th?
שנאמר ויאמר אליהם *Shene'emar vayomer aleihem*, משה *Moshe* said to them, בן
מאה ועשרים שנה אנכי היום *ben mea ve'esrim shana anochi hayom*. I
am 120 years old today. לא אוכל עוד לצאת ולבוא *Lo uchal
od latzeis velavo*. I cannot any longer come in and go, שאין
*she'ein* The idea is that somebody, it's dictated how many years a
person will live, and if they're righteous, they fill it out the
entirety of the year. So they die on the same day they're
born, they live out the full number of years, the fullness of
the year, שנאמר את מספר ימיך אמלא, et mispar yamecha amaleh, and
the number of your days I will fill.
Actually, first day of the second year? Right? Next year. If you've
had your birthday, it's already in the first day of the upcoming
year.
I don't know what to say about that. Okay, תניא, maybe you
die before your actual hour of birth. תניא רבי שמעון בן יוחי
אומר, Tanya Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai omer, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai says,
שלש מצות נצטוו ישראל בכניסתן לארץ ונוהגת בין בארץ בין בחוצה לארץ,
Shalosh mitzvot nitzvu Yisrael bichnisatan la'aretz v'noheget bein ba'aretz bein b'chutz la'aretz,
they were commanded three mitzvot when they entered into the land. We're
back to the issue of חדש, Chadash, ערלה, Orlah, כלאים. Kilayim. So
he understands that this is those three. I'm sorry, well, let's take
a look. שלש מצות נצטוו, Shalosh mitzvot nitzvu, they were commanded.
Okay, one minute. Yeah, this is חדש, Chadash ערלה, Orlah, כלאים. Kilayim.
So the exact three that we said apply outside of the land
of Israel, he said those three applied when they entered the land,
בכניסתן לארץ, bichnisatan la'aretz, ונוהגת בין בארץ בין בחוצה לארץ. ve'noheget bein
ba'aretz bein b'chutz la'aretz. So yes, they only began when they entered
the land, but they apply even outside of the land. Okay, so
that is חדש, Chadash ערלה, Orlah, and כלאים. Kilayim. ערלה Orlah and
כלאים Kilayim is agreed, חדש Chadash is debated, and he says that
all of those three apply, so he also says like רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer that חדש Chadash applies in חוצה לארץ. chutz la'aretz. Okay,
והוא הדין שיינהגו, ve'hu hadin she'yanagu, and it makes sense that they
should apply out of the land of Israel. Why does it make
sense? ומה חדש שאין איסורו איסור עולם ואין איסורו איסור הנאה ויש
היתר לאיסורו נוהג בין בארץ בין בחוצה לארץ. u'mah Chadash she'ein issuro
issur olam ve'ein issuro issur hana'ah ve'yesh heter l'issuro noheg bein ba'aretz
bein b'chutz la'aretz. He starts with a presumption that חדש Chadash applies
outside of the land. Why? 'Cause that's how he says בכל מושבותיכם,
be'chol moshvoteichem, means wherever you dwell. So חדש Chadash applies outside of
the land. Now חדש Chadash of those three is the weakest of
those three. Why is it the weakest? Number one, אין איסורו איסור
עולם, ein issuro issur olam, it doesn't remain asur. The grain that
started off as חדש Chadash comes the עומר and then it becomes
מותר. mutar. So it's not a permanent איסור. issur. Number two, ואין
איסורו איסור הנאה. ve'ein issuro issur hana'ah. חדש Chadash is not asur
in הנאה. hana'ah. You can't eat it but you can get הנאה
hana'ah from it. Number three, ויש היתר לאיסורו, ve'yesh heter l'issuro, and
it becomes permissible. Now what does it mean it becomes permissible? How's
that different than אין איסורו איסור עולם? ein issuro issur olam? So
רש״י Rashi says that it means, it's a little complicated, תוספות Tosafot
has a lot of explanations what that means, but anyway רש״י Rashi
says what it means is it's not איסור עולם issur olam because
it stops, it doesn't apply after the day of the 16th. Once
it's the 17th of ניסן it's מותר. mutar. Not only that, if
you bring the עומר it becomes מותר mutar even on the 16th
itself. So ויש היתר לאיסורו ve'yesh heter l'issuro is sort of like
a variation, a day early, a half a day early. Okay, but
anyway תוספות Tosafot has a couple other explanations what איסור עולם issur
olam means. Anyway going on he says, and anyway it has all
those leniencies and even with that fact that it's a weak prohibition,
נוהג בין בארץ בין בחוצה לארץ, noheg bein ba'aretz bein b'chutz la'aretz,
it applies even out of the land. כלאים שאיסורן איסור עולם, Kilayim
she'issuran issur olam, כלאים Kilayim is always asur. כלאים? Kilayim?
I thought we were talking about ערלה?
Orlah? We're going to get to ערלה. Orlah. ואיסורן איסור הנאה, ve'issuran
issur hana'ah, I skip a line? No. ואיסורן איסור הנאה, ve'issuran issur
hana'ah, you cannot derive benefit from כלאים. Kilayim. ואין היתר לאיסורן, ve'ein
heter l'issuran, also doesn't become permissible. אינו דין שינהוג בין בארץ בין
בחוצה לארץ, eino din she'yanogu bein ba'aretz bein b'chutz la'aretz, how much
more so should that apply in חוצה לארץ. chutz la'aretz. והוא הדין
לערלה משתיים, ve'hu hadin l'Orlah mish'tayim, and ערלה Orlah has two of
those three. What are the, what is the one that it does,
that it doesn't have? So it's not asur לעולם. le'olam. Right, רש״י
says it's not asur לעולם. le'olam. Of course תוספות Tosafot, says I
don't understand, the fruit that grew in the first three years is
asur לעולם. le'olam. The tree isn't asur לעולם. le'olam. The tree becomes
permissible, the fruit of the tree becomes permissible in the fourth year.
So something like that. Anyway,
so therefore he says we start with the fact that חדש Chadash
applies in חוצה לארץ chutz la'aretz and these two also. So not
only does he say חדש Chadash. apply in חוצה לארץ, chutz la'aretz,
it sounds like he's saying that the איסור issur of ערלה Orlah
and כלאים Kilayim in חוצה לארץ chutz la'aretz is דאורייתא. de'oraita. Right?
We were saying the other day that it's only דרבנן, de'rabbanan, הלכה
למשה מסיני. halacha l'Moshe m'Sinai.
He says like it's דאורייתא. de'oraita. חדש chadash is דאורייתא de'oraita in
חוצה לארץ chutz la'aretz and these two as well. Now of course
תוספות Tosafot asks the obvious question. If you look at תוספות, Tosafot
תוספות Tosafot says ואם תאמר, ve'im tomar, the last תוספות tosafot on
ל״ח lamed chet thirty-eight, טבל ותרומה ומעשר נילף קל וחומר מחדש דנוהג
בין בארץ בין בחוצה לארץ. tevel u'terumah u'ma'aser neilef kal v'chomer mi'Chadash
d'noheg bein ba'aretz bein b'chutz la'aretz. If that's true, just say all
the הארץ כל מצות ha'aretz kol mitzvot apply in חוצה לארץ chutz
la'aretz based on a קל וחומר kal v'chomer from חדש. chadash Right?
Good question. Yes. שהרי איסורו איסור עולם ואין היתר לאיסורו she'harei issuro
issur olam ve'ein heter l'issuro in that טבל ותרומה. tevel u'terumah. ויש
לומר, ve'yesh lomar, דף ל״ח daf lamed chet thirty-eight, תוספות tosafot says
דאיכא למפרך מה לחדש שכן אין בשאלה תרומה ומעשר שישנן בשאלה. de'ika
l'mifrach mah l'Chadash sheken ein b'she'eilah terumah u'ma'aser sheyeshan b'she'eilah.
So he has different types of answers, but שאלה she'eilah meaning because
you can do, you can go to a חכם chacham and say
I changed my mind I didn't want to take תרומה terumah on
this part of the grain, you know I want to take תרומה
terumah on different grain not on this grain. Because תרומה terumah is
a הפלאה, hafla'ah, it's like a נדר, neder, right? So therefore since
you could sort of reverse your taking of תרומה, terumah, that's somehow,
basically another way of saying that is that תרומה... terumah... תרומה terumah
and מעשר ma'aser and all those things get their status through a
human act, whereas חדש chadash gets the status, you know, independent of
your act. You make something תרומה terumah and מעשר. ma'aser. Anyway, why
that should be a basis of a difference is not clear. But
the question is more interesting I think than the answer, which is
if you're using until now we said everything has to be taken
separately. We start by the presumption that anything agricultural is only in
the land of Israel, and if you want to make any exceptions
you have to prove the exceptions. And חדש chadash. we're debating, and
ערלה orlah and כלאים kilayim maybe is a דרבנן derabanan or הלכה
למשה מסיני. halacha l'moshe misinai. Now we're saying חדש chadash, is דאורייתא
de'oraisa out of Israel and everything will learn from a קל וחומר
kal vachomer from חדש. chadash, So then it really like opens up
the Pandora's box to say everything applies in חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz.
Okay, anyway, one minute. So that's one minute.
That's רבי שמעון בר יוחאי. Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. רבי אלעזר ברבי
שמעון אומר, Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon omer, Rabbi Elazar his son says,
כל מצוה שנצטוו ישראל קודם כניסתם לארץ נוהגת בין בארץ בין בחוצה
לארץ. kol mitzvah shenitztavu Yisrael kodem knisatam la'aretz noheget bein ba'aretz bein
b'chutza la'aretz. Anything that applied before they entered in the land is
not dependent on the land, and therefore it applies out of the
land. But לאחר כניסתם לארץ, l'achar knisatam la'aretz, if it only applied
once they entered the land,
like חדש, chadash, ערלה, orlah, כלאים, kilayim, אינה נוהגת אלא בארץ. einah
noheget ela ba'aretz. It's only applied in the land of Israel. So
I guess he disagrees with his father and he says you're wrong.
חדש, chadash, ערלה, orlah, כלאים, kilayim, anything that only began once they
entered in the land is clearly limited to the land.
נצטוו nitzavu means began as opposed to being commanded. Everything was commanded
before.
Right, right. חוץ מן השמטת כספים ושילוח עבדים, chutz min hashmattat kesafim
v'shiluach avadim, with the exception of annulling the debts on שמיטה shemittah
and sending free the slaves on the יובל, yovel, שאף על פי
שנצטוו לאחר כניסתם לארץ, she'af al pi shenitztavu l'achar knisatam la'aretz, even
though it says there that it applies once you enter into the
land, נוהגת בין בארץ בין בחוצה לארץ, noheget bein ba'aretz bein b'chutza
la'aretz, it's applied whether in or out of the land. Okay, so
basically the debate here we'll talk about שמיטה shemittah and עבדים avadim
in a minute, but the debate is, right? It basically is a
way of reframing the issue of the משנה. mishnah. חדש, chadash ערלה,
orlah, and כלאים kilayim are things that are land dependent. So one
way of calling the way it's being framed here, Michael's correct, it's
not that they were commanded once they entered the land. It means
that the command began to be applicable once they entered to the
land. These things are land dependent, they should be limited to the
land of Israel, which is what רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar
b'Rabbi Shimon said. However, his father רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon
bar Yochai says no, there are a few things that only applied
once they entered in the land that are land dependent, but once
they began to apply, applied even in out of the land. And
that is the things mentioned in the משנה, mishnah, חדש, chadash, ערלה,
orlah, כלאים. kilayim. And he seems to say, רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
that it applies even דאורייתא de'oraisa out of the land. Whereas רבי
אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, the son of רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, seems to
completely reject that they apply outside the land of Israel. Yes, Michael.
Just these things aren't exactly all the same because חדש Chadash, applies
to the grain of the non-Jews planted, and כלאים kilayim too, right?
Some of כלאים kilayim like whatever, whereas ערלה orlah is only of
your planted, in other words it says נטעתכם. nitatchem.
I hear your point, but that was the תוספות tosafot we dealt
with yesterday, that תוספות tosafot actually points out based on the ירושלמי
Yerushalmi that the ירושלמי Yerushalmi seems to feel that everything mentioned in
the משנה mishnah applies even from non even if non-Jewish planted, and
that's why תוספות tosafot had his whole discussion about how they could
eat from the grapes of the non-Jews if there's an ערלה orlah
problem.
But I don't understand that, what do you do with נטעתכם nitatchem
though?
I don't know, I hear, I'd have to look at what the
מדרש הלכה midrash halacha says, but תוספות at least that was exactly
the תוספות we dealt with yesterday. Okay, yes.
What did we say previously about contradicting your father, can you do
it in terms?
Yes, exactly. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara. says like this. Now
okay so we have the debate of חדש, Chadash. ערלה, orlah, כלאים,
kilayim, do they apply in חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz and if so
is it דאורייתא, de'oraisa, דרבנן, derabanan, what's its status? But now we
also look at why do they have to say that שילוח עבדים
shiluach avadim and השמטת כספים hashmattat kesafim apply even in חוץ לארץ,
chutz la'aretz, even if the even if the Torah speaks about when
you enter the land, but those are not land-based מצוות. mitzvot. Shouldn't
those obviously apply in חוץ לארץ? chutz la'aretz? Why did you even
have to spell that out? Right? Other things say when you enter
into the land, right? It speaks about like we said before, תפילין,
tefillin, פטר חמור, peter chamor, there are things that the תורה says
when you enter the land, but we are working with the assumption
that the phrasing when you enter the land is not in itself
significant. It has to be a land-based מצוה, mitzvah, right, based on
the dirt, on the soil, in order to think that it's limited
to the land. So why does he say have to point out
that these two are not limited to the land? Obviously they're not,
they're not soil related. So the גמרא gemara says, let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
השמטת
כספים חובת הגוף היא, hashmattat kesafim chovat haguf hi, annulling loans, that's
a personal obligation. Of course it applies outside of the land of
Israel.
No, לא נצרכא אלא לכדתניא, lo nitzrecha ela l'chidetanya, we need it
for what we teach in the ברייתא. דתניא רבי אומר, detanya rabbi
omer, וזה דבר השמיטה שמוט, v'zeh devar hashemittah shamot, this is the
law of the
שמיטה, shemittah, release, כל בעל משה ידו אשר ישה ברעהו, kol ba'al
masheh yado asher yasheh v're'ehu, all of your loans. So why does
it say השמיטה שמוט? hashemittah shamot? בשתי שמיתות הכתוב מדבר. bishtei shemittot
hakatuv medaber. talking about two types of
שמיטה. Shemitah. אחת שמיטת קרקע ואחת שמיטת כספים. Achat shemitat karka ve'achat
shemitat kesafim. One is releasing the land, okay, and or you know
not working the land, and the other is releasing the loans. בזמן
שאתה משמט קרקע אתה משמט כספים. Bizman she'atah meshamet karka atah meshamet
kesafim. When you don't work the land then you don't then you
then you annul the loans. בזמן שאי אתה משמט קרקע Bizman she'ei
atah meshamet karka if there's a time when שמיטה Shemitah does not
apply, when when שמיטה Shemitah not apply before you enter let's say
the land of Israel or let's say when there's no when you're
exiled, when there's no יובל, Yovel, okay, without יובל Yovel there's no
שמיטה, Shemitah, okay, and there's only יובל Yovel if most of the
Jews are living in the land of Israel, so for various reasons
שמיטה Shemitah isn't applying. בזמן שאי אתה משמט קרקע אי אתה משמט
כספים, Bizman she'ei atah meshamet karka ei atah meshamet kesafim, there's no
annulling of loans. So since חוץ... Chutz...
well we're going to see. But since the annulling of loans is
dependent on the practice of the of the שמיטה Shemitah of the
land, so now you're seeing what we what I would have thought.
Therefore I would have thought ואימא ve'eima I would say במקום שאתה
משמט קרקע אתה משמט כספים ובמקום שאין אתה משמט קרקע אין אתה
משמט כספים. bemakom she'atah meshamet karka atah meshamet kesafim u'vemakom she'ein atah
meshamet karka ein atah meshamet kesafim. So I would have logically said
therefore maybe the שמיטה Shemitah of loans only applies biblically in the
land of Israel. Since it only applies when there's a when there
is שמיטה Shemitah of קרקע, karka, maybe it's the geographically it only
applies where there is שמיטה Shemitah of קרקע, karka, which by the
way is a very reasonable read of the פסוקים, right? שמיטה Shemitah
is something that takes place in the land of Israel, everybody right
וקראתם דרור בארץ לכל יושביה, ukratem dror ba'aretz lechol yoshveiha, that's regarding
יובל, Yovel, but anyway, but the point is it's an experience of
Israel, right, of the you know of the שמיטה Shemitah year in
Israel. So out of Israel maybe there would be no releasing of
loans. So
therefore תלמוד לומר כי קרא שמיטה לה' מכל מקום. talmud lomar ki
kara shemitah l'Hashem mikol makom. No, the שמיטה's Shemitah been declared for
God and here מכל מקום mikol makom literally means מכל מקום. mikol
makom. Well מכל מקום mikol makom means regardless, but here it means
in מכל מקום. mikol makom. Oh it does say מכל מקום, mikol
makom, oh well. But מכל מקום mikol makom here also means מכל
מקום. mikol makom. Anyway, regardless, you know, even though it's even though
you're not in the land of Israel there's an idea that שמיטה
Shemitah applies everywhere. שמיטה Shemitah applies regardless of the an aspect of
שמיטה Shemitah applies regardless of the שמיטה Shemitah of קרקע karka and
that is the annulling of loans. That being said I should say
that you know that there's like in the time of the ראשונים,
Rishonim, some people were extremely lenient not even to bother writing a
פרוזבול, Pruzbul, and the ראשונים Rishonim had to deal with the fact
about how come if there's this מצוה mitzvah of שמיטת כספים shemitat
kesafim and the only way you get around it is writing a
פרוזבול, Pruzbul, how come people completely ignore פרוזבול Pruzbul or they just
do a tiny trivial thing that shouldn't really count? And according to
a number of ראשונים, Rishonim, שמיטת כספים shemitat kesafim outside of the
land of Israel, not only is only דרבנן derabbanan nowadays but is
only like a מנהג חסידות, minhag chasidut, you know. So there actually
is the הוה אמינא hava amina of this גמרא Gemara is not
so crazy. There are some ראשונים Rishonim that actually think that שמיטת
כספים shemitat kesafim really is limited to the land of Israel, okay,
when שמיטה Shemitah is נוהג. noheg. Now we have two things: we're
in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz and שמיטה Shemitah isn't נוהג. noheg. Okay,
but according to רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rebbi Elazar beRebbi Shimon it's
not dependent and even in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz and even when
there's no שמיטת קרקע shemitat karka in the land of... well actually
I'm sorry, there are two things. Nowadays he would probably say that
it's דרבנן derabbanan because he says it is dependent on the practice
of שמיטת קרקע shemitat karka in Israel, okay. So nowadays if you
don't have a יובל Yovel and you don't have שמיטת קרקע shemitat
karka in Israel at a דאורייתא de'oraita level, so if there's no
שמיטת קרקע shemitat karka at a דאורייתא de'oraita level there's also no
שמיטת כספים. shemitat kesafim. That dependency he does have, that it's only
applied when there is שמיטת קרקע shemitat karka in Israel. Okay, but
but if there is שמיטה Shemitah in Israel, then for him שמיטת
כספים shemitat kesafim applies in חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz at a דאורייתא
de'oraita level. Okay, so it requires the practice of שמיטת קרקע shemitat
karka in Israel but it is not limited geographically to Israel. And
that's what the פסוק is teaching.
That's his opinion though.
That's his opinion. Now that's number one. Possibly, correct.
Now you need to have the שמיטה Shemitah would be דאורייתא de'oraita
in Israel. What what...
Well the minimum, and that's what I was saying, is that you
would need there to be the יובל Yovel would have to be
practiced. And for יובל Yovel it says וקראתם דרור בארץ לכל יושביה,
ukratem dror ba'aretz lechol yoshveiha,
to all its inhabitants, which means בזמן שכל יושביה עליה. bizman shechol
yoshveiha aleiha. So according to the גמרא Gemara you need to have
at least representatives if not the majority of all twelve tribes living
in Israel, you know, and each one in its right tribal location.
So we haven't had יובל Yovel practiced at a דאורייתא de'oraita level
since the towards the end of בית ראשון, bayit rishon, you know,
from the time סנחריב Sancheriv exiled the you know the the ten
tribes. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
so that's why I needed the פסוק to tell me that שמיטת
כספים shemitat kesafim applies outside of Israel. The other thing that applies
outside of Israel is freeing the slaves. Now you ask me that's
a big חידוש chiddush too, right? Did you ever hear the idea
that during the יובל Yovel year if you're living in France and
you have slaves you have to free them? Right, presumably we think
the יובל Yovel year's only so you know is in Israel. So
actually the גמרא Gemara is going to say this is obvious because
it's not land based, but it actually is a חידוש. chiddush. So
the גמרא Gemara says שילוח עבדים חובת הגוף היא. shiluach avadim chovat
haguf hi. Of course you have to free your slaves outside of
Israel. That's a personal obligation. That's not land based. based on the
soil. So again this gets to the point I made yesterday which
is that there are some things that are dependent on the land
that are national based but not soil based, you know? And the
גמרא Gemara sort of is ignoring that. Like the just the line
we said a minute ago, שלוש מצוות נצטוו ישראל בכניסתם לארץ. shelosha
mitzvot nitztavu Yisrael bechnisatam la'aretz.
Do people know where that phrase usually appears? Usually, I mean רמב"ם
Rambam quotes it, that's how people I think know it. שלוש מצוות
נצטוו ישראל בכניסתם לארץ. shelosha mitzvot nitztavu Yisrael bechnisatam la'aretz. Number one
is להעמיד להם מלך. lehamid lahem melech. Number two is לבנות בית
הבחירה. livnot beis habechirah.
And the third I think is להכרית זרעו של עמלק. lehachrit zaro
shel Amalek. Okay?
That has nothing to do with the soil. That has to do
with issues of like national identity, right? So this is sort of
being highlighted here. פשיטא, pshita, of course you do שילוח עבדים אחוץ!
shilluach avadim achutz! It's not פשיטא. pshita. It's not soil-based but it
is has to do with like a type of a national experience,
right? So anyway it is funny that the גמרא Gemara here is
only seeing this through the lens of like soil-based מצוות. mitzvot. So
the גמרא Gemara says שילוח עבדים, shilluach avadim, of course you do
it out of Israel, חובת הגוף היא, chovat haguf hee, it's a
personal obligation. No, סלקא דעתך אמינא salka da'atach amina I would have
thought הא כתיב וקראתם דרור
בארץ, ha ketiv ukeratem dror ba'aretz, you shall proclaim liberty throughout the
land to all its inhabitants thereof. בארץ אין בחוץ לארץ לא, ba'aretz
in, bechutz la'aretz lo, it's only an experience in the land of
Israel, not out of the land of Israel. תלמוד לומר יובל היא.
Talmud lomar yovel hee. No, it is the jubilee year, מכל מקום,
mikol makom,
regardless, even if you're not living in Israel. אם כן מה תלמוד
לומר בארץ? Im ken mah talmud lomar ba'aretz? So why does it
say in the land? בזמן, bizman, similar to what we said before
about the annulling of loans. בזמן שהדרור נוהג בארץ נוהג בחוץ לארץ.
Bizman shehadrur noheg ba'aretz, noheg bechutz la'aretz. When there is freedom proclaimed
in Israel, when the יובל yovel applies in Israel, it applies outside
of Israel. בזמן שאין דרור נוהג בארץ אינו נוהג בחוץ לארץ, Bizman
she'ein dror noheg ba'aretz, eino noheg bechutz la'aretz, if it's not applying
in Israel for various reasons, maybe בית דין beit din didn't sanctify
the the year, maybe there's not יושביה עליה, yoshveha aleha, whatever the
case might be, אינו נוהג בחוץ לארץ eino noheg bechutz la'aretz it
would not. So similar to the annulling of loans, it is a...
it's an extension of the experience in Israel. It has to be
taking place in Israel to take place out of Israel. It starts
in Israel. But ultimately, once it starts, it applies everywhere. Yes.
To be fair, in the Torah's view, they probably weren't thinking of
anyone
living outside of Israel anyway. Well, yes, that's exactly the point, that
you know, that's what I sort of said before, like we discussed
the other day about the position sort of of the רמב"ן Ramban
that even the חובת הגוף chovat haguf מצוות mitzvot are primarily seen
as like this is, you know, exile is national death. Exile is
an unnatural state of being. It's not like fundamentally Judaism is a
religion, the way we tend to think of it, oh Judaism is
a religion, it's universal. There are some things that are soil-based that
you have to be in Israel for. That's not the way the
Torah thinks about it. The Torah thinks about it as Judaism is
a national identity and the Torah and the מצוות, mitzvot, not Judaism
anyway, the Torah and the מצוות mitzvot are the laws of the
Jewish of the Israelite people living in the land of Israel and
any other state of being is a, you know, is a not
only an aberration, it's almost like it's
the classic argument of Leo Pinsker's Auto-Emancipation that since we've been living
in exile outside of our national entity for so many centuries
that
we think that that's natural and normal and that's a pathology of
Jewish consciousness.
There you go.
Right, right.
It's a perverted way of seeing our own identity.
So that's what, you know, the רמב"ן Ramban says is that any
idea that any מצוות mitzvot apply out of Israel is the חידוש,
chiddush, it's not the reverse. It's not to try to figure out
which מצוות mitzvot are soil-based and apply in Israel. It's like why
should anything apply out of Israel? So anyway. All right, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
תנן התם. tenan hatam. Now we taught over there in ערלה, Orlah,
I read you this משנה Mishnah the other day. Back to חדש,
Chadash we're not letting up with
חדש. Chadash תנן התם. tenan hatam. See, couldn't have asked for a
better timing of this discussion.
How did he link this into the first פרק perek of קידושין?
Kiddushin? No seriously.
It's all the כל מצוות. kol mitzvot. First we have a categorizing
of all of the various קניינים, kinyanim, and like we just take
all the קניינים kinyanim and we try to sort of organize them,
and then we take מצוות mitzvot and we try to categorize and
organize.
Because isn't this a type of קניין kinyan as it were? Like
people to God?
No, no, no. I mean I mean no, I don't think so.
I think we're just going by category. תנן התם: tenan hatam: החדש
אסור מן התורה בכל מקום. hachadash assur min hatorah bechol makom. חדש
Chadash is אסור assur everywhere. That's I said this משנה, Mishnah, the
סתם משנה stam Mishnah is רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, that חדש applies
in the בחוץ לארץ, bechutz la'aretz, which is the big halakhic question:
do you go by this סתם משנה stam Mishnah and then חדש
applies in
בחוץ לארץ? bechutz la'aretz? ערלה הלכה, Orlah Halakhah, ערלה Orlah presumably הלכה
למשה מסיני Halakhah leMoshe miSinai although we'll see about that in a
minute, וכלאיים מדברי סופרים, vekilayim midivrei soferim, כלאיים Kilayim is rabbinic. מאי
הלכה? mai Halakhah? So the גמרא asks what does הלכה Halakhah mean?
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל הלכות מדינה, amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel
Hilkhot Medina, which is a very interesting answer, which רש"י Rashi says
means it's like a דרבנן. derabbanan. I don't know what הלכות מדינה
Hilkhot Medina means. רש"י Rashi says הלכות מדינה Hilkhot Medina means, where's
רש"י? Rashi? הנהיגו הם
עליהם בחוץ לארץ.
hinhigu ha'hem aleihem
bechutz la'aretz.
It's almost makes it like a מנהג. minhag. This is just the
practice we have.
And how about מדברי סופרים? midivrei soferim?
Well מדברי סופרים midivrei soferim is that it's legislated from above. This
is just we
practice, right, right. נוהג noheg and והלכה, veHalakhah, right. So yeah just
the practice the accepted practice. עולא אמר רבי יוחנן Ulla Amar Rabbi
Yochanan no, הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai. No, no, no, it's
like a tradition going back to to הר סיני. Har Sinai. It's
not a פסוק in the Torah but it's weightier than a דרבנן.
d'rabbanan. אמר ליה עולא, Amar lei Ulla, that's normally how we read
it. אמר ליה עולא לרב יהודה Amar lei Ulla leRav Yehuda so
עולא Ulla said to רב יהודה Rav Yehuda who said
it's הלכתא מדינה. Hilchosa Medinah. בשלמא לדידי דאמינא הלכה למשה מסיני Bishlama
l'didi d'amina Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai ערלה's Orlah weighty, היינו דתנן להו בין
ספק ערלה לספק כלאים. Hainu d'shnan lo bein safek Orlah l'safek Kilayim.
That's why we have a difference between ספק ערלה safek Orlah which
is weightier and ספק כלאים safek Kilayim which is more lenient. What's
the difference? דתנן, Detnan, ספק ערלה. safek Orlah. Here what do you
do if you have a doubt whether something is ערלה? Orlah? בארץ
Ba'aretz if it's in the land of Israel אסור assur because it's
ספק דאורייתא. safek de'oraisa. Okay
בסוריה, b'Surya, סוריה Surya which has a lands like you know right
juxtaposing to the land of Israel where maybe דוד המלך David HaMelech
conquered and so on and have some דרבנן d'rabbanan status of קדושת
ארץ ישראל. Kedushas Eretz Yisrael. So מותר, muttar, we're lenient if there's
a doubt. Okay so even in סוריה Surya because it doesn't have
a real status of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. ובחוץ לארץ U'vechutz la'aretz
if it's even further away from the land not only is ספק
ערלה safek Orlah permissible but יורד ולוקח. yored v'lokeach. You can go
into the orchard there and buy from the farmer even though you
know that the farmer either he has some trees that are ערלה
Orlah and some that are not, it's not a hundred percent ערלה,
Orlah, but you go down and you buy from him and you
can ובלבד שלא יראנו לוקט u'vilvad shelo yirenu lokeit as long as
you don't directly see him taking from the ערלה Orlah tree. You
can sort of almost it's sort of like מבטלין איסור לכתחילה, m'vatlin
issur l'chatchila, right. Yeah you can like close your eyes, go pick
from a tree I'm not going to look which tree you're picking
from and then he comes back and then you buy from him,
you know don't ask don't tell as long as I have some
doubt I'm okay. That's ערלה, Orlah, okay. Now how about כלאים? Kilayim?
Now that seems lenient enough but let's compare to כלאים. Kilayim. ואילו
גבי כלאים תנן כרם הנטוע ירק ירק. V'ilu gabei Kilayim tnan kerem
hanatua yerek yerek. You have a vineyard that has some you know
vegetables growing nearby. It's got some barley growing nearby?
Yeah
well different than the vineyard. Okay the vineyard and the vegetables is
a כלאים. Kilayim. וירק נמכר חוצה לו V'yerek nimkar chutzah lo and
then right there you've got a whole big thing by the side
of the highway, a whole big vineyard with some barley patches, and
right at the edge of the highway you've got somebody with a
little vegetable stand selling barley. Okay so it's a pretty reasonable assumption
that the barley came from the vineyard and is כלאים. Kilayim. This
is in חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, okay. בארץ אסור, Ba'aretz assur, don't
buy that barley in, I said barley I'm sorry I keep saying
barley I meant to say broccoli, I don't know why I'm saying
barley, anyway I mean broccoli would be true about barley too. Anyway
you got some broccoli and asparagus being sold right by the highway
stand right near the vineyard and it's growing there, you also see
patches of it growing with the vineyard. So okay בארץ אסור, Ba'aretz
assur, in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael don't buy the broccoli and the
asparagus. בסוריה מותר, B'Surya muttar, in סוריה Surya you're allowed to. ובחוץ
לארץ יורד ולוקט ובלבד שלא ילקוט ביד. U'vechutz la'aretz yored v'loket u'vilvad
shelo yilkot b'yad. In חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz you can see actually
the now the non-Jew go and you can observe him picking it
as long as you don't pick directly. Now that sounds crazy, that
sounds the simple פשט of that is that it sounds like even
if you see him picking the כלאים Kilayim and you know it's
a hundred percent כלאים Kilayim as long as you didn't pick it
it's okay. כלאים Kilayim meaning broccoli that was nourished by asparagus soil.
Yeah well actually it's growing with the vineyard. Yeah so just it's
I just so the עיקר ikkar here the key more is that
it's growing together with the vine. Okay so anyway so this sounds
so whatever is going on here the גמרא makes it sound like
it's a level of ספק. safek. רש"י Rashi sort of says later
that if you look but anyway that that you didn't pick directly
so and you didn't you know but but so as long as
there's some doubt for you it certainly seems that it's something that's
even more obviously a problem and nevertheless it's okay. So he says
I understand why. I think that they're both that that one is
הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai the ערלה Orlah so we're a
little stricter that you know and here where the כלאים Kilayim is
rabbinic we're even more lenient. אלא לדידך Ellu l'didach but according to
you ניתני הא וזו יורד ולוקח הא וזו יורד ולוקט. nisni ozah
v'zos yored v'lokeach ozah v'zos yored v'lokeit. According to you if they're
both דרבנן, d'rabbanan, I mean ערלה Orlah when you say הלכתא מדינה
Hilchosa Medinah that sounds like it's even weaker than a דרבנן. d'rabbanan.
So then they should both have the same standards, why are there
different standards? Okay so we did that a little quickly we'll pick
up with that tomorrow but the basic point is in both cases
ספק safek is מותר. muttar. Not only is a ספק safek מותר
muttar but even almost like a willful ignorance is מותר muttar in
both cases. But nevertheless it seems like כלאים Kilayim is even more
lenient than ערלה. Orlah. So if you say ערלה's Orlah הלכה למשה
מסיני Halacha L'Moshe MiSinai and כלאים Kilayim is דרבנן d'rabbanan you can
understand the different levels. But if you say they're both דרבנן, d'rabbanan,
הלכתא Hilchos means הלכתא מדינה, Hilchosa Medinah, then how do you explain
why there are different levels of how lenient we are in cases
of ספק? safek? Okay so to be continued tomorrow.